Guide to the Ekaterina Konstantinovna Breshko-Breshkovskaia Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ekaterina Breshko-Breshkovskaia papers
1911-1931
MS 606
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
Manuscripts, articles, and printed material by and about Ekaterina K. Breshko-Breshkovskaia. Items are in Russian and are largely undated.
Breshko-Breshkovskai͡a, Ekaterina Konstantinovna, 1844-1934
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain Catherine Breshkovsky's manuscript "How I went Among the People;" various handwritten manuscripts about herself and about the people she encountered and part of her reminiscences. There are also two articles in manuscript form written by E. E. Lazarev in 1931 and M. M. Rosenbaum in 1917 about Catherine Breshkovsky and also miscellaneous articles from magazines and newspapers about her life.
Biographical / Historical
Ekaterina Konstantinovna Breshko-Breshkovskaia, 1844-1934
"The Little Grandmother of the Russian Revolution"
Catherine Breshkovsky, as she was known in the United States, was one of the early revolutionary workers. She was the first woman to be sent to the mines for a political offense and spent most of her life either in prison or in exile. (From 1871-1917 she spent 14 years in prison camps; 13 years in penal servitude in Siberia; 10 years in conspiratory work; 6 years under strict surveillance by the police; 2 years in exile out of the country and only 8 months, in 1917, of freedom in her work in Russia.)
Throughout her life she exerted great energy in her unrelenting struggle to bring democracy to the people of her country. She showed extreme patriotism and her love for the Russian people was unbounded. Her confidence in the final outcome of the struggle for freedom, in which she was engaged, was unshakable. Her absolute unselfishness and her constant thoughtfulness for the welfare and happiness of others was one of her greatest assets. She never complained of the injustice and hardship which she personally endured, but alwaysstroveto help others and never lost hope or failed in courage.
Women revolutionaries -- Soviet Union; Women; Europe; Soviet Union -- History -- Revolution, 1917-1921; Breshko-Breshkovskai͡a, Ekaterina Konstantinovna, 1844-1934
- Inventory
  - "How I went Among the People" [typed manuscript]
    - Pages 1-100 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Pages 101-200 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Pages 201-300 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Pages 301-400 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Pages 401-476 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Various handwritten manuscripts about herself and about the people she encountered, some dated, 18 pp. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cajnyj Listok [Tea Leaf], outline, 3 pp. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Grandmother," E. K. Breshko-Breshkovskaia about herself, 9 pp. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Numerous other untitled manuscripts concerning her life and people she encountered, some dated, 23 pp. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Articles written about E. K. Breshko-Breshkovskaia (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Rasskaz." E. E. Lazarev, short story, 2 pp., 1931 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - S Babuskoj [With Grandmother]. M. M. Rosenbaum, 11 pp., 1917 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Pamphlet in memory of the 80 th birthday of E. K. Breshko-Breshkovskaia. Outline of her life, 1844-1929, Paris. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Traits from the Life of E. K. Breshko-Breshkovskaia." Evgenij Kolosov. Ezmesjacnij Zurnal, no. 5-6, pp. 216-227., undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Obvinitel'nij Akt." [Accusatory Act] Supplement to Znameni Trud No. 30, 12 pp., undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Vesti o Babuske." [News about "Grandmother"]. Za Narod [For the People], no. 43, 16 pp., 1911 October (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Vosmidesjatiletije E. K. Bresko-Breskovskoj." [80 th Birthday of Breshko-Breshkovskaia]. Dni[Days], no. 370., 1924 January 26 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Extract from Memoirs. Dni [Days], Berlin, 5 pp., 1924 January 20 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - From My Reminiscences: How I met the Grand Revolution. 12 pp. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Manuscript dictated by "Grandmother" to A. P. Toporkov. 58 pp., 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - My Stay in Russia from 1896-1903. 10 pp. (Box 1, Folder 10)